Welcome in to another episode of
Dolphins HQ. And my guest today is none
other than head coach of your Miami
Dolphins, Jeff Hafley. Coach, welcome
in, man.
>> Thanks, man. It's good to be on. Uh,
it's good to be here.
>> I'm happy to have you. And we met you at
Thursday at your introduction press
conference. And I'm sure this week has
been a total whirlwind for you here and
sort of a two-parter to kind of keep
going in that direction with whirlwinds.
But what has this first week been like?
And then as you get ready for the
combine, the kind of the next big temple
event, what does it look like from now
until the combine?
>> Yeah. Well, one, we just I feel like I
just got here. I mean, what's today?
Monday. I mean, this was my interview
day. So, a week ago at this time, I'm
get I'm still in the hotel room getting
ready to interview and then suddenly I
get the job and I'm at the national
championship game. Uh, flew home. Then I
flew back for the presser and really
since then, it's been about hiring the
staff and that's really priority number
one cuz you got to surround yourself
with good people and building a staff
starting with the coordinators, then to
the assistants to the quality control
coaches. That's been the biggest focus.
Um, the next step will be for me to to
contact all the players on the roster.
So, those are really like 1A and 1B and
and that's really what we're working on
right now. And then certainly when that
is done, then I'll I'll get ready for
the combine, start watching some guys in
the draft. We got to watch free agents.
Um, watching our roster. There's a lot
to do. It's not all going to happen in
one day. And and that's what I learned
in my first stint as a head coach. You
just you got to just continually work
every single day. do the best you can,
get some rest, and wake up and do it
again.
>> Do you draw back at all in your time at
Boston College as a head coach in the
college level where you're doing
recruiting? Is that kind of similar to
contacting the Dolphins players and kind
of getting yourself familiar with with
what you got here?
>> I think the start of hiring a staff
certainly is. And you know, I look back
to the mistakes that I made and um you
know, this has helped me. I feel more
comfortable this go around having done
it before. And then, you know,
evaluating recruits and evaluating free
agents, there's some similarities, but
in the last two years being back in the
NFL, I mean, I had a big role in
evaluating the defense, looking at the
roster, looking at free agents, watching
every player on the defensive side of
the ball for the draft, and now it's
just going to be doing so on offense and
special teams as well. I think the last
two years, you know, basically being the
head coach of the defense with Matt
really running the offense, um, has also
given me, uh, a good lesson on what it's
going to be like. So, going back a
little bit further to your origins back
in your college playing days and
becoming a coach, I saw the injuries in
college kind of put you into more of a
coach's position back in those days
where you would spend time in the booth
with the coaches and doing some film
work. How did that experience help
prepare you for a life in coaching?
>> Yeah, that's something that we really
haven't talked about. Um, when I was in
college, I had to have surgery twice on
both legs. So, while I was recovering
and trying to come back to play, um,
yeah, I hadn't even thought about that
in a while. the coaches, they brought me
to the away games and in the home games.
I was up in the booth and I was almost
like a student coach at the time. They
just I was always in the office and I
was always around them. I probably was
in the office more than I was actually
in school and going to classes cuz I
wanted to watch film and I think they
were like, "This guy probably watches
more tape than we do." So, they started
to have me help him coach and then
eventually I came back and played. But
that was one of the moments where I knew
it's what I wanted to do and it
certainly it helped me uh figure it out
pretty quick.
>> You majored in football sounds like
>> I did. I I was a I was a history major.
Um but I probably remember more football
and more plays that have happened in my
career than I do of what I learned in
history.
>> Sure.
>> My history is what happened in every
game that we've played and coached in
and try not to make the same mistakes.
But don't ask me any history questions,
please.
>> Totally fine. When I was in college, I
was more into watching Dolphins games on
VHS tape than I was in
>> VHS tapes. That dates you. Most of these
people have no clue what a VHS tape is.
>> But in reading material for this
interview, coach, the impression I got
was that the reason you wanted to come
back to the NFL was to put the whistle
around your neck, get your feet back on
the grass, and just coach football. You
love coaching. It's your happy place,
right? Why do you think that is? Like,
why why is that your happy place, for
lack of a better term?
>> Um, I love to teach. I love the
competitiveness of it. I love being
around the guys. I love game planning. I
love watching tape. Um, but mostly I
like to get out on the field and teach
fundamentals and technique. I like to be
hands-on. Um, and I like to see, you
know, when you work really hard on on
doing everything you can to get a player
better and then you see him have success
or you see the drill work translate to
the field. I mean, that's a really cool
feeling. And part of that is helping
change people's lives and taking them
from where they are to where they want
to be and helping them accomplish their
goals. Uh that's always been a big part
of why I do what I do. And then there's
nothing like being in a locker room
after a win. When you get a bunch of
grown men hugging and some in tears and
just embracing and you know even in some
of the defeats, I mean just those
moments, the highs and the lows, I don't
know if there's another profession like
it. Um and and towards the end when I
was in college, you know, those were it
wasn't the case. it was more, you know,
trying to keep the players, talking to
agents, trying to recruit other college
players, doing things that really
weren't coaching. Um, and that's why I
kind of made the jump back.
>> Yeah, makes perfect sense. And, and
doing some of the watching some of the
interviews you've done in the past, I
I've seen you talk about the shifting
landscape. I saw an interview we talked
about Boston College of going from
single high to, you know, split field
presentations and coverage principles
and zone landmarks and vision on the
quarterback, all that stuff. How do you
balance
>> football guy? He's a football guy right
here.
>> I try to be. I mean,
>> you can tell he watched tape. He's not,
for all those listening, he wasn't
lying. He actually knows what he's
talking about.
>> I do I do enjoy watching tape. It's one
of my favorite things to do. But how do
you balance
>> How did you coach then?
>> I'm changing the interview now. It's my
turn. Then how come you didn't get in
the coaching?
>> You know, I went to Washington State. I
was uh I love watching Mike Leech and
just I guess I just never never made
that jump. I don't know.
>> It sounds like you missed your calling.
>> I think I I think I might have.
>> We might have to interview this when I'm
done with more of a personnel. I like I
like doing the scouting stuff.
>> I can put it in a good word for you.
>> Can you?
>> He's looking for staff right now. So
maybe you should think about
interviewing.
>> Well, I mean, I'm blushing on my own
show right here, so I really appreciate
that.
>> I'll let you do the interview again.
>> Um, the question is, how do you balance
the complexities of not just teaching
it, but maybe, you know, putting
yourself in the perspective of the
player where you're thinking like, how
can I make this, you know, complex for
the opponent, but as simple for them to
understand as possible.
>> Yeah. Um, one, I think a lot of coaches
get, um, over complicated in scheme.
This is still a player's game, and the
players have to, they need to be able to
execute what you call. I mean, I could
draw up three blitzes that, you know, I
I think will be protection or, you know,
win the down, but if the players can't
understand it and learn it and it's not
going to work, it doesn't matter how
smart I think I am because it's not
going to work, right? So, the way I
always teach is part to whole. I'm big
on, you know, teaching a technique
within a call and making sure everybody
understands all of those techniques. And
then once those techniques are taught,
then I teach the whole and I drop those
pieces in so I can become more complex
with me doing the thinking. And
sometimes those calls might be a little
wordier so I'll do the thinking where I
want them to just be able to play fast
and not think because when you think you
stink. I mean that's the olding the
oldest coaching cliche that there is. I
just think a lot of coaches think
they're smarter than they are and that's
no disrespect because at times I do as
well. But we have to understand that the
players have to know and really
understand so they can play fast. So
it's part to whole teaching for me and
then it's constant. I want feedback from
the players all the time. What do you
think? Is this too much? Can you can you
do it? Do you like it? Is it make sense?
And then what's big for me is when I
teach and install, I always want
everybody to understand the why of
everything. Because I think if you
understand the why, and I don't just
throw up a pressure and say this, this,
this, and this. But when you teach the
why, I think people can learn better.
And going back to our conversation, I
wanted to be a teacher. Like I wanted to
be a history teacher. Even though I
really don't know much about history, I
wanted to be a history teacher because
I've always enjoyed teaching and I
always felt one of my strengths was
taking something complicated and making
someone making it easier for people. So
those are really big in how I coach
defense.
>> Does that apply to you in all walks of
life? Like can you take that to your
kids and like teach them how to change a
brake pad or something, you know,
something in life?
>> I couldn't do anything with a brake pad.
me uh my wife would have a better shot
of that than I am. Um one I don't think
my kids listen to me when I coach them
on anything,
>> but yeah, I think I can explain things
well. Um some things better than others,
but
>> maybe they'll start listening to me a
little bit, but they're tough on me
right now. So,
>> especially the seven-year-old,
>> she's the one I'm telling you where if
we don't have a good game, she lets me
know pretty quickly.
>> Oh, man. The kids will be brutally
honest and tell you whatever they uh
whatever comes to mind, they're going to
tell you,
>> which is a good thing. That's how
everybody should be.
>> Yeah. Exactly. The truth tellers.
Exactly. So, we're going to get more
into the weeds here for you real quick.
So, I watched every third and long play
you guys had last year with the Packers.
>> We were good on third and long.
>> Very good on third and long.
>> Third and medium, not so good.
>> It was so fun to watch though, man,
because like I I would see you would
overload the pressure look and then you
would bring the blitz from the backside
in the secondary. I'm like, I don't
know. Like, I you said to yourself, I I
kind of know a little bit of ball, but I
don't know what I'm watching when I'm
watching your defense because it's
pretty hard to decipher. And in getting
ready for this interview, I'm kind of
looking around some of the other head
coaches in the league. Like Sean McVey,
for instance, has a uh a a core tenant
that he talks about. Simple for us,
brutal for them, easy reads, hard
choices for opponents. And again,
watching that, I just kind of got lost
in the sauce on that. How do you go
about implementing that philosophy of,
you know, complex for us, but easily
digestible for players.
>> Yeah, that's I mean, that's kind of what
I was just talking about. I want it to
look very very confusing to the offense
and everything that we do. And it all
goes back to the way you teach and the
way you install. um you know it is
simple for us, complex for them and
that's how we want it to be. So
everything that we do each game we kind
of present a different structure and I
want to try to confuse them off of what
we've showed in the past and they think
they're going to get one thing and then
they get the other thing and that has a
lot to do with studying ourselves. Um
and the players taking pride and I
always talk to them about being the best
disguised team in the NFL. So we take a
lot of pride and time in that and pay
attention to the details of that and
that goes back to the words and what we
call things. So within a course of a
game, imagine learning a glossery of
techniques. I can easily throw out a
different word and the players be like,
"Yeah, no problem." Because that's how
we teach and we can change up our
disguise and the pressure instantly
throughout the course of a game. And
that's really how we've developed our
system um to do so. So that is huge for
us like you're saying with an offense um
shifting and motioning and trying to
confuse you, but it's still they're just
running outside zone, which is not very
complicated. So, it's more of an
illusion of of uh being complex than it
really is being complex. And you need
guys to take pride in that.
>> Makes perfect sense. You also discussed
at your introduction press conference
four core principles. Trust, belief,
toughness, extreme accountability. Could
you take us through each of those, what
that looks like, and how you landed on
that on that exact collection of
pillars, if you will.
>> Yeah. I mean, those are just, I think,
the important things in building
relationships. And I think that's the
number one thing that we're going to
have to do here. And it starts with
trust. Whether it's with me and you, uh,
whether it's with anybody here. And I
said this in my press conference, and I
can elaborate a little bit more.
Everybody always hears, "Oh, he's so
slow to trust, or he doesn't trust
anyone, or you know, the way that he um
went through life, he has a hard time
time trusting people, a hard time
trusting males, a hard time trusting
anybody." I mean, that's I respect that,
right? And I understand that. So, I'm
not going to sit here and say right now,
you're you're just going to trust me.
Like, why would you? You don't know me.
So, you probably shouldn't trust me, so
be careful. Um, so what I want to do
with everybody that I meet is I want to
earn it. And how do I do that? Um,
there's a lot of ways. What I tell you
I'm going to do, I'm going to follow
through with, right? Um, the way that I
treat you and the way that I show up and
be consistent every single day, the way
I say I'm going to, because to me, and
I'll tell the players, I see better than
I hear, right? It's actions speak louder
than words. It's however you want to
throw out these cliches. But I think
that's really important and I think over
time that builds trust. Now, at the same
time, I'm going to make it a two-way
street. I mean, I'm not going to trust
you right now. I'm kind of joking cuz
>> you shouldn't though.
>> Part of me does trust you for some weird
reason, but not not truthfully yet, but
I I want to I want the players to
understand that it is a two-way street
and that what they say they need to
follow through with, and what they tell
me they need to follow through with. And
over time, I think then you build it
from the ground up. And I think that's
the start of a relationship. Um, I
talked about belief because even coming
back to the NFL,
I think there's still a lack of
confidence in a lot of players and just
a lot of people in general. And whether
it's a young kid or whether it's an
adult, I mean, it's a hard world and in
order to succeed in anything, you have
to believe in yourself. And I think I
can help that. And I think my job is to
show them that I believe in them to get
them to them believe in themselves. And
I think once they do that, then they'll
start believing in each other. And then
that becomes a very, very powerful
thing. And I like to think back to the
time I got to Green Bay and I believe we
had a defense that started to believe in
themselves. And I had players even
towards the end tell me, "Thank you for
believing in me." And I think that's
very, very powerful. Once that hits and
you can kind of see I'm going in steps
on building a relationship or building a
team. I think you have to be a connected
team. I think I have to connect with the
players and I have to connect with all
different types of players, right? Um
and that takes time and that takes a lot
of effort and a lot of energy. But I
don't think you can lead anybody unless
you truly get to know them and are
connected with them. Because the way I
want to coach and I want to coach them
really hard and I want to hold them to
an extreme level of accountability,
all those things I just talked about
have to be your foundation because then
the next step is an extreme level of
accountability to themselves, to their
teammates. That's like the glue that
holds everything together that I just
talked about. And that is going to be my
job early on to hold these guys
accountable. And hopefully after all
this happens, they start holding each
other accountable. But that has to start
with the individual which helps with me
and then it goes to the rest of the team
and those have always been my steps to
try to develop culture which everybody
throws around. They say well what's your
culture what here I'm just explain to
you on how we're going to build a
culture and then if we do all those
things
>> you'll see what it looks like where I
won't have to talk and tell you what it
looks like right because again I see
better than I hear. And then I talked
about a toughness. And that's not a
toughness where I'm just going to shove
you or pitch you. It's it's it's a
physical and mental toughness that you
have to live every single day. And
that's very very hard. That's waking up
on time. It's showing up on time. It's
doing the extra work. It's doing what
you're supposed to do when you're
supposed to do it the best that you can
and doing it over and over and over. And
that takes a mental toughness. And then
our game is a physical game. And there
has to be a physical toughness in the
way we want to play at all levels.
Whether you're a wide out or a corner or
a long snapper or a kicker, it doesn't
matter. There has to be a toughness on
the field of how hard we play. And
again, it's not one that it's talked
about. It's turn on the tape and watch
us run to the ball or watch us block
down the field or watch the wide
receiver block for his buddy, which all
goes back to how much do you care about
each other, right? Because I firmly
believe on defense, I always talk about
when you hit the pause button, you can
find out how much a guy loves his
teammate by how close he is to the
football.
>> Sure.
>> Right. And I'm going to show him that.
So, those are the things that are
important to me. Um, and I know that's a
little long- winded, but I believe
that's what it's going to take as we get
started.
>> You're on the right show for long-winded
right here. It kind of sounds like a
self- sustained like ecosystem. like it
kind of you you set it in motion and
then it takes care of itself and you
obviously you have to manage that going
forward but it kind of sounds like
that's the idea of getting players and
everyone to kind of buy into the system
so that they're the ones managing it
overall.
>> Yeah. I mean once once the players are
the leaders then it becomes real. When I
can turn to a guy and say handle that
for me
>> you're close. When a player handles it
because he sees it
>> then you got him because the standard
you walk by is a standard you set right?
So, if people are just walking by saying
that's okay, that's not good enough.
>> Sure.
>> You talked about uh you know installing
that trust in Green Bay and that first
year you had four player four rookies
take over 400 snaps that season and this
year you talked about this in your press
conference. You get Micah Parsons what
two weeks before the opening game and
you guys actually blitzed more with
Micah Parsons. So, your ability to adapt
was always I thought really impressive
to watch on tape. But when you think
about, you know, whether it's adapting
your scheme to fit a new player or going
to a different level of football to
adapt or just in a game if a opponent
comes out with something that you
weren't expecting and you have to adapt,
just talk to me about the importance of
adaptability as a coach and as a
program.
>> Yeah, I just think in general, I've
never been one to say, "This is my
playbook. This is my system. We're going
to run this." When I got to Green Bay,
they were a 3-4 team. We switched it to
4-3. They were, "How are you going to do
that? Why are you going to do it?" Well,
I looked at the personnel. It's what I
felt we could do to have the most
success. and we were very successful.
Right then we're really playing 34
spacing, 4-3 spacing, which a football
guy like him understands what I'm
talking about.
>> Some people right here watching this
might say, "Who knows?" Well, you can
call him and ask him, he'll explain.
>> So, I was really going into more of a
mindset coming into this season that in
base defense, we were we had Kenny
Clark, we had some bigger guys, we were
going to be different than we were. And
then a week before our first game, we
lose Kenny and add Micah, which which is
great. you get one of the best football
players in the world, but you lose Kenny
who is also a really good player too and
a phenomenal human being. So then a week
I had to figure out how to use Micah,
which totally was going to be different
than I how I was plan all offseason and
all training camp. So adaptability, the
the ability to be innovative and change,
right? Again, if you teach with words
and people understand part the whole,
you can switch. So then we had a ton of
success um early on with Micah and then
we lost him, we lost Dvonte Wy, we lost
Vaness. So, we started losing pieces.
So, then we had to adapt and go back and
do different things. It's just I believe
it's what you have to do and I believe
that's good coaching. It's like what are
we going to look like on offense? I have
a pretty good idea of what, you know,
hiring Bobby, what we're going to look
like on offense. Let's figure out who
our players are as we get going and we
have to put them in the best position to
succeed.
>> You mentioned Bobby House. My next
question right there, Bobby Slo and
Chris Taber are official hires here for
the Miami Dolphins. What can you tell us
about both of those guys off the top
here? phenomenal people and I think you
have to when you look at hiring a staff
which we're doing now the number one is
you win with people and we're going to
go through adversity together so you
have to have people that you trust that
when things get hard aren't going to
change who they are and they're going to
rise up and those are two people that
I've been around I was with Taber in
Cleveland and I was with Bobby in San
Francisco are two great people um that
are built the right way and then they're
really good football coaches Bobby was
actually on the defensive side of the
ball with me when I was in San
Francisco. So, we were together all the
time. Like, he was my right-hand man on
defense. Now, Bobby's brilliant and Kyle
Shanahan's brilliant. And what Kyle
usually does is he takes the guys he
thinks are the smartest guys on the
staff and he moves them over to offense.
So, it doesn't surprise me that he took
Bobby to be an offensive coach. So, now
Bobby's got the defensive background.
Now, he gets the K Kyle Shanahan
background. So, he's got really good
pedigree. And then he gets to go call it
in uh Houston where he coached the
rookie of the year in year one. uh went
to two playoff runs and it didn't work
out that second year for him. Um and
then I continued to stay in touch. He
came here and then he's with Mike who
has a ton of respect for him as well and
I do with Mike as a play caller and a
coach in general. I think he's awesome.
And um I got a chance to hire him and to
me that became a no-brainer. And with
Taber the same thing. I mean Taber you
know a guy I was with in Cleveland. He's
one of the most respected special teams
coaches in all the National Football
League. And what that allows me to do is
not have to worry as much about that
unit because I have full trust in him
where I can focus on being the head
coach and getting the defense ready when
the season comes.
>> So this is a simple one and we'll close
with the fun ones. So when a media
pundit looks at your team or an opposing
team comes down here, watches you on
tape, whatever it might be, and they
say, "Man, Jeff Halfley's Dolphins are
blank." What do you want that blank to
be? How do you want people to perceive
your football team?
>> Physical. I mean, one word to me, it's
you'd like to you'd like to say that's
the most physical team, the toughest
team that we're going to play all year.
I mean, and those are the controllables,
right? The scheme, the the roster.
There's no um there's no reason that we
shouldn't be the most physical team when
you turn on the tape.
>> What does that look like in terms of
developing that? Is it is it personnel?
Is it coaching? A combination of both of
those things? combination of everything
we just talked about from how I
described to you. We were going to reach
our culture. That's that's all that that
is and that's everything we do every
single day. So when you turn on the
tape, it's a bunch of guys playing as
hard as they can for each other. Uh as
physical as they can for each other. Um
and that's that's what we're looking
for. And like I said, that's going to
start April 6th.
>> Reminds me of a quote that Kyle Vanoi
once told me, you set the edge on I
think it was Saturday. Set the edge on
Saturday on defense right before the
game happens. So, we talked about some
of the the football stuff. There are
some some fun ones here for you. Some
personal stuff here. Rapid fire. Some of
your favorite.
>> I'm not good at rapid fire. So, I'm just
warning you. I don't mind interviews. I
stink at rapid fire. So, if I give you a
funny look, just ask me the next
question.
>> We'll see if it makes the cut or not.
So, it's just about your favorite things
in life. Do you have a favorite movie?
>> Yeah. Any of the Rocky series.
>> Perfect.
>> Yeah, probably the original because it
was original and really cool, but I'm a
big Stallone fan. I like Bruce
Springsteen and Sylvester Stallone.
Shocker. Um, those two usually tie
together, so I'll go with Rocky.
>> They must They must subscribe to your
four principles. I think those are guys
that
>> those are tough guys right there. And
the boss is the boss.
>> There you go. How about your meal?
Favorite food?
>> Chicken parm.
>> That's mine, too.
>> Yeah. See, I knew I liked you.
>> Couple of football guys here. What about
your favorite downtime activity or
hobby?
>> Just hanging out with my family.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I don't I don't have many hobbies.
Just go home and hang out with them.
>> Yeah. It's all it's timeconsuming with
the with three little ones myself. As a
father of three little ones, I always
love hearing this perspective from
parents. What do you think has been the
most fun age yet for your little ones?
>> I would say I think they're at a fun age
now. My youngest is seven, Leah is
seven, and Hope's 10. I think they're
both very different. So, here's what
I've seen with kids. Same parents,
totally different kids. So, Hope at
seven is way different than Leah at
seven, right? So, I don't know if I can
group them in ages, but they're at a fun
point right now. Um, you know, so I
would say I I would say any age.
>> The last one here. I'm a big music guy.
Do you have a favorite song, musical
genre, band?
>> Springsteen.
>> I'm from New Jersey.
>> All right. Perfect.
>> I mean, gosh, I love Springsteen. So,
yeah.
>> Favorite song by him.
>> Oh gosh. Um,
>> spot here.
>> I like so many of his song. I'll say
Thunder Road.
>> Great. Great way to close it right
there. Dolphins head coach Jeff Hafley.
Coach, we appreciate your time today,
man.
>> Thanks.
>> Thanks, man. This was a pleasure. Thank
you.